ALOY: So the waters came fast?
LAULAI: One day it was dry, the next the nearby river
had risen and the entire basin was flooded.
I don't understand it.
There was no rain, not even any clouds.
And yet the river rose higher than I'd ever seen it.
And there it remains.
A flood without rain, that is strange.
Where is this place?
I'll have a look if I'm in the area.
Just northwest of here.
Look all you like, but I don't see what good it will do.
The flood waters aren't going anywhere.
How does one ask a river to relent?
This must be the ruin Laulai was talking about, Deep Din.
Flooded too, like she said.
Snapmaws.
Probably came from somewhere up river.
Follow the river, find the source. Seems simple enough.
These mountains must be the Icerasps.
The Shaman's Path begins somewhere up above.
There, that must be where the water is coming from.
Looks like something from the Old Ones.
Well, somebody wanted in.
Nearly blew this entire ledge off just to get through the door.
COMPUTER: Flooding detected, evacuation recommended.
COMPUTER: Overflow basin compromised.
ALOY: The "overflow basin" — is that the Din?
Looks like a control centre.
What happened in here to start the water flowing?
I should be able to shut this place down from here.
Ugh, someone made a mess of this.
Hmm, if I had the right parts, I'll bet I could get it working again.
The lock positions, helpful.
A piece is missing.
Not getting in there without it.
Rough waters, no way I'd be able to swim.
Maybe my Focus will see something.
Someone's been through here, not that long ago either.
DISTANT VOICE: Help! I've … er … I've become trapped somehow.
DISTANT VOICE: By the forge,
I'm glad to hear another person stomping about in here.
DISTANT VOICE: This blasted door is stuck.
DISTANT VOICE: This is a perfect opportunity to do a good deed.
DISTANT VOICE: And clear your conscience
for whatever cruelties you may have committed.
Whoa! Ooof!
ALOY: Are you all right?
[laughs]
You don't know how happy you just made me.
Haha! For a moment, I thought my fire was snuffed.
My forge gone cold, but no.
Nope, not old Gildun.
You're … welcome?
Uh, wait, start from the beginning.
What are you doing down here?
Oh! My apologies.
When you mostly talk to yourself,
you can tell your stories in whatever order you like.
There's an artefact in that storage room I simply must acquire.
But as you may have noticed, the door won't budge.
I took one of those roundish ringy whatsits from the wall beside the door.
No luck.
So I had to go with that panel with the button, even less luck!
My gentle experimentation caused the chamber to … um … flood. A little.
So I pushed the button again, perhaps a little too enthusiastically.
Sparks and smoke!
So you found the button that controls the flow of water.
Quite by accident.
And then you broke that button.
Also quite by accident.
GILDUN: Now, obviously, I came here to investigate.
My cautious footsteps may have contributed, slightly, to the collapse of a bridge.
When the bridge began to collapse I may have, for the sake of expedience, abandoned the cumbersome ringy whatsit to the waves.
By the time I thought to give up the endeavour, the door had closed behind me.
And thusly do we come to the present moment.
Well, there's no way we're getting into that storage room without another ring.
It's part of a locking mechanism that controls the door.
I'll grant you that adds a heretofore undiscussed
level of complexity to the proceedings.
You said something about an artefact?
Indeed!
That storage room is brimming with treasures from the Old Ones.
But one in particular caught my eye.
An intricate looking glass!
I've only seen one such device before.
My old mum brought one back for me from … from …
… wherever she got to that time.
I remember holding it, staring into its face, seeing myself and…
…and my mother just over my shoulder, smiling.
And one of these looking glasses it's in the storage room?
Oh, yes, I'm quite sure.
I peered into that dim little chamber and there it was.
I've wanted to find for so long, I…
How're we gonna get that ring?
Two sets of hands, girl. Two sets of hands!
Behind us lie a pair of enormous gates.
But I believe the gates must be operated in tandem.
Together we can dry this place out.
Guess we'd better get started then.
I guess we'd better!
GILDUN: Up ahead, girl, see the valve?
GILDUN: Time to put our hands to use.
GILDUN: I'll take care of this one.
GILDUN: There's another valve on the other side to lock the gate in place.
GILDUN: Would you mind heading across and, er, doing the honours?
GILDUN: You know, I'm reminded of a delve I undertook out near The Claim.
GILDUN: A stone ruin, cloud-tall and lake-wide.
GILDUN: Must have been thirteen levels on that monstrosity, but no walls.
GILDUN: Just great stone columns bearing the weight of the level above.
GILDUN: Filled out with row upon row
of those enormous, rusted-out Old World carts.
GILDUN: You know the ones with four wheels?
GILDUN: I've scraped through a hundred of those carts.
GILDUN: But the only things I've ever seen inside is birds nests.
GILDUN: You don't suppose that's what they're for do you?
ALOY: A tub of stagnant water, charming.
GILDUN: Why would the Old Ones want to cart around families of birds?
GILDUN: Marvellous, you made it!
GILDUN: Now grab that valve and give it a spin!
ALOY: On it.
GILDUN: A little more now and I should be able to get the blasted thing moving.
ALOY: There, you should be able to lower the gate.
GILDUN: Right you are.
GILDUN: Now, when I get this gate down, you'll need to turn the valve again.
GILDUN: Gotta lock this thing in place.
ALOY: One gate down!
GILDUN: Halfway through then, aren't we? To the second gate!
GILDUN: A ladder is a rare and special thing, girl.
GILDUN: You can depend on it to take you
exactly where you need to go and no further.
GILDUN: Hmm, I'd wager the valves for the
second sluice gate are somewhere above us.
GILDUN: But how are we gonna get up there?
ALOY: Let me look around, see what I can find.
ALOY: Looks like I could jump across on that rickety rusting platform.
ALOY: Might find a way up.
GILDUN: Nice jump!
GILDUN: [laughs] Nice, what am I saying? That was stupendous!
GILDUN: I've never seen such absolute disregard for personal safety.
ALOY: Thanks, I think?
GILDUN: Oh, you're close, girl. Just spring across the gap.
GILDUN: Ha?! You're right above me!
Just send that ladder on down.
ALOY: Look out below!
GILDUN: Now we've done this once before.
GILDUN: Should be as easy as falling down a hole.
GILDUN: If you take the valve on the other side…
ALOY: If it's set up the same way on this side, I should look for an access tunnel.
GILDUN: This? This is my sort of delve.
GILDUN: A thousand little problems to solve.
GILDUN: A million minute and invisible factors.
GILDUN: My father used to say to me "Gildling"
— he'd call me Gildling — "Gildling" he used to say,
GILDUN: "Don't make the delve harder than it needs to be."
GILDUN: "The best delves are done in
half the time it takes a campfire to sputter out."
GILDUN: Now, my father was a great man, mind you.
GILDUN: But dead wrong when it came
to choosing a rubric by which to judge delve quality.
GILDUN: To find yourself stuck, then unstuck.
GILDUN: To fail, then succeed.
GILDUN: To get lost, and to find yourself.
GILDUN: That's what makes a delve!
ALOY: Uh-huh, Gildun.
ALOY: Okay, Gildun, turn the valve!
GILDUN: It's not working!
GILDUN: Damn thing's too heavy.
GILDUN: Glance behind me, would you?
GILDUN: See anything big and, er, broken?
ALOY: Looks like part of the counterweight broke off.
ALOY: If I can get up there, my weight might be enough to get it moving again.
ALOY: Hang on, okay? I've got a plan.
ALOY: I need to get up higher.
ALOY: Could climb up that wreckage, that's pretty much what I do now.
ALOY: Can't jump straight to the counterweight from here.
ALOY: But I could climb higher, get above it.
GILDUN: Stop! The drop's too far, girl!
GILDUN: Oh, [laughs] controlled falling, very clever.
ALOY: Going down!
ALOY: Almost low enough to jump.
GILDUN: You can make it!
GILDUN: Let's see another one of those mad leaps! Haha!
ALOY: Got it. We're good to go.
GILDUN: You were a sight to see.
GILDUN: Bounding from metal rust trap to metal rust trap. [laughs]
GILDUN: Still a bit of water, but low enough wouldn't you say?
GILDUN: Now then, er, where is that ring?
ALOY: Good question. Well, at least I should be able to swim now.
GILDUN: Snapmaw! It's a Snapmaw! Very, very big Snapmaw!
ALOY: I see it, Gildun!
GILDUN: Very big, very, very big.
ALOY: Just stay out of the way!
GILDUN: Forge forgive me, what if that Snapmaw swallowed that ring we're after?
GILDUN: Just gobbled it right up?
ALOY: We'll find out after I've killed it!
GILDUN: Is it dead? Just tell me when it'd dead, would you?
ALOY: It's dead.
GILDUN: Ha! Marvellous.
GILDUN: So the uh ring, maybe if you pry its jaws open and reach inside.
GILDUN: I can't look.
ALOY: You were right, this thing did swallow the ring.
GILDUN: Haha! That's the old Gildun intuition in action!
GILDUN: It's never led me astray.
GILDUN: Sure, it's chosen routes could be a bit circuitous, but…
GILDUN: Never mind! To the storage room! To the spoils!
GILDUN: Ooh, what's in here?
GILDUN: More old world treasures perhaps?
GILDUN: This place is full of surprises.
GILDUN: Could we have a look?
ALOY: Didn't you want to get into the storage room?
GILDUN: I do, fervently!
GILDUN: But, well, I got time to poke my nose in if you do.
ALOY: We drained enough water for what we need to do, but…
ALOY: I wonder if I could empty out the whole dam.
ALOY: Pipes, valves, maybe I can drain the rest of the water from here.
ALOY: Perhaps my Focus can help me.
ALOY: Sure are a lot of valves.
ALOY: Should check my Focus first.
ALOY: Alright, time to get the flow going to the right place.
GILDUN: I say this as a man typically enamoured of complexities, but…
GILDUN: This looks like it might be a little much for me.
ALOY: Don't worry, I think I've got this.
GILDUN: Music to my ears! To each job its proper tools.
GILDUN: Toothpicks make horrible arrows as the saying goes.
ALOY: That's not quite right.
ALOY: Looks like I'm on the right track.
ALOY: Something's not right.
GILDUN: You got a competent mind, girl.
GILDUN: A mind for nuance and finesse.
GILDUN: Not I, no indeed. Not Old Gildun.
ALOY: There, one step closer.
GILDUN: This job demands a certain degree of patience, doesn't it?
GILDUN: I'm afraid I inherited my mother's restlessness.
ALOY: Getting there.
GILDUN: You've been at this a while, girl.
GILDUN: No room to judge, mind.
ALOY: There, that should do it.
ALOY: I should head back and see if that took care of the rest of the water.
GILDUN: Got it working, did you?
GILDUN: [laughs] Of course you did!
GILDUN: Never met a conundrum you couldn't unconundrum, have ya?
ALOY: The door's open. Guess it had sealed because of the flooding.
ALOY: This must go down to the lower level.
ALOY: Ugh, it stinks down here.
GILDUN: [sniffs] Mmm-mmm, you smell that?
GILDUN: Smells like a forgeside morning in The Claim.
RECORDING: LAURA: See? Check this out!
RECORDING: LAURA: We can just bang on this pipe, you know?
[banging sounds]
RECORDING: SHELLEY: Could we sample that, or…?
RECORDING: LAURA: Totally, like what about after the… uh, sorry, just a sec.
RECORDING: SHELLEY: Laura?
RECORDING: LAURA: I, uh…
RECORDING: LAURA: I need to take a break.
RECORDING: SHELLEY: Laura? Hey! Laura!
ALOY: Looks like that's everything. I should head back up with Gildun.
GILDUN: So, as we circle back around to the matter of the supply room.
GILDUN: I can't wait, I can't wait, I can't wait!
GILDUN: Almost there!
GILDUN: Soon I'll hold the looking glass in my hand, just like mom and I used to.
GILDUN: Err, what, um…?
GILDUN: What are you doing with your hands there, girl?
GILDUN: [laughs] I can't believe that worked!
GILDUN: I thought you'd lost your mind, tickling the empty air like that.
Gildun? Everything okay?
I was so sure I saw it.
The looking glass.
I was so sure.
Right there in the window.
I would…
Of course, a trick of the light. Nothing at all.
I'm sorry, Gildun. It must have meant a lot to you.
Oh well, much as any artefact of the Old Ones would mean to me, really.
It's fine, I'm fine.
Besides, what are the spoils compared to the delve?
That's why we do it, girl!
The delve, not the treasure.
And what a delve it was!
By the great blazing forge, I'll never forget that.
Now then I, uh, believe we have some repairs to make.
RECORDING: SHELLEY: I mean, this is it.
RECORDING: SHELLEY: We get to play together, what, maybe two more times?
RECORDING: LAURA: Nah, Shells. Farewell tour! Reunion tour in like, six months.
RECORDING: LAURA: Bands do it all the time.
RECORDING: SHELLEY: For our adoring fans?
RECORDING: LAURA: It's not that hard to stay in touch, Shelley.
RECORDING: LAURA: We could practice in holospace.
RECORDING: SHELLEY: People always say that.
Okay, let's fix the panel and shut this place down.
GILDUN: Ohhh that's a whole lot prettier, isn't it?
[laughs]
What does it mean?
It means it worked.
By the forge, you are a wonder!
Do you hear that often? I'll hazard a guess you do.
I've heard something like that once or twice.
Oh, she's modest now?
A master of the arts of the Old Ones, a delver to shame the entire Claim!
And she wants to be modest. Ha!
It's not like I did it alone, Gildun.
No. No, I suppose not.
So what's next for you, on your way back to The Claim?
And deprive the people of Song's Edge the story of this encounter?
Perish the thought!
I'll stay there a while longer.
But a story is best told by all who encountered it.
Come and lend a hand, won't you?
COMPUTER: Overflow basin empty, interior accessible.
COMPUTER: Minimal flood damage.
ALOY: Sounds like the basin has dried out too, maybe I'll take a look.
GILDUN: Another adventure so soon? You're braver than me!
GILDUN: But there was no question of that. [laughs]
GILDUN: You go on ahead.
GILDUN: I'm gonna stand right here and bask in our victory for a while longer.
Water's lower.
And going by that sound, I think Laulai's already at the Din.
It's an animal figurine.
The shape looks familiar.
She wasn't kidding about the sound.
I've been seen.
It felt that!
Right on target.
It'd be fascinating if they weren't looking for me.
That hurt it!
Must be the entrance to this "Din".
Ouch!
RECORDING: LAURA: Live from the illustrious Overflow Basin Studios
RECORDING: LAURA: it's Concrete Beach Party!
A-one, a-two, a-one-two-three-four!
You look happy to be playing again.
I don't know what you did, but the water drained in the snap of a short song.
What do you think of the music?
I've never heard anything else like it.
That's because there's no other place with such resonance,
such intonation that rattles your ribs with its power.
And of course, no-one else knows these pipes like I do.
I learned them by ear before I could walk, strapped to my father's back.
Thank you for draining the waters.
Not just for myself, but for my ancestors and their songs.
Please, take this as a token of our gratitude.
LAULAI: Let's see, what shall I play next?
LAULAI: The echoes are different off wet stone, sound is warmer.
LAULAI: The sound of the pipes fills my heart with joy and sadness all at once.